Hi i'm Andy I'm one of the Pharmacists at
the Great Yarmouth Store, I'm here to talk
to you a little bit about NMS, the new medicine
service, we're going to be going over all
parts of the service and what you can do to
help us.
The new medicine service, NMS, is a service
we provide for patients starting a new medication
for one of the conditions listed on your screen
now.
People often have problems when they start
a new medication, NMS allows us to support
those patients with any problems they may
face in those initial weeks.
Our aim is to help patients take their medication
safely and more effectively.
This in turn results in savings for the NHS,
whilst improving our patients quality of life.
The service is made of three main stages,
Initially you have the engagement stage, which
is when we speak to the patient before they
start taking their medication
We’ll see if they’re eligible for NMS
and ask if they’re interested in the service.
We’ll obtain their written consent, and
agree on the best way we can contact them.
This can be on the phone or in person.
The intervention stage is 1-2 weeks after
starting the new medication.
The pharmacist will speak with the patient
about how they take their medcine, and identify
any barriers which prevent them from taking
it.
This is where the pharmacist can give advice
to the patient, and if anything serious has
come up, they can be referred to the GP.
Now if they’re going to continue with the
medication, they'll agree a time for the follow
up stage.
The follow up stage is 2-3 weeks after the
intervention stage.
It’s a similar conversation to the intervention
stage, but the pharmacist will follow up anything
any prior issues
They’ll reinforce the benefits of the medicine,
and ensure it’s being taken as prescribed.
Again, at any point if any issues that arisen
since the intervention, they can still be
referred to the GP.
The engagement stage is where you can really
help us.
Identifying and signing patients up for NMS
can be undertaken by anyone in the pharmacy.
Every time you sign a patient up for NMS,
you give them the best possible chance of
getting the most benefit from that medicine.
To help demonstrate this we’ll be following
Rob.
He’s been prescribed a new inhaler for his
asthma.
So when rob hands in a prescription, we’ll
ask him one simple question
“Are any of these medications new for you?”
In this case, Rob has a new inhaler, so we’ll
place a small star to the right hand side
of the new drug.
This highlights to the pharmacist what medicines
are new.
To give you a better idea of what medication
is eligible for NMS, let’s go to the dispensary.
So here's some medication you might see under
NMS.
So you're looking for inhalers, that's for
Asthma or COPD
Got your blood pressure medication there,
your antiplatelet or anticoagulation medication
And finally, medication used for type two
diabetes
Doesn't matter if you don't know all the medication
under NMS, but it's great if you know some
Rob’s been prescribed a new salbutamol inhaler,
this medication is eligible for NMS, so we’ll
check if he’s using it for a target condition
Are you using this for Asthma?
Yes, I am,
So after confirming the medication is for
a target condition, and it’s within NMS,
you can sign them up!
Now ensure you explain the consent form to
the patient, speak to your pharmacy manager
for a more detailed explanation of this.
If they’re happy to continue, ensure they
sign and date the form, then confirm their
phone number, or agree on a good time to come
into the pharmacy.
But what if you haven’t seen the patient?
If you’re labelling their medication, a
quick glance at their records may indicate
if it’s new.
If you think it is, star the medication on
the prescription and add a consent form to
the basket if you think it might be an NMS.
When the pharmacist hands out the medication,
they will be able to confirm if the patient
is eligible to take part in the new medicines
service.
Rob has not had this inhaler before so the
pharmacist will discuss things with him like
the benefits and side effects
And In one to two weeks’ time, we’ill
give him a call, and see how he is getting
along.
Something as simple as a phone call could
make a huge difference to someone’s health.
Rob’s asthma is under far better control
thanks to NMS, turns out he wasn’t using
the inhaler as intended.
Thanks to the new medicine service, he is
making far greater gains from his medication.
But Rob’s not alone, data shows that nearly
1 in 5 patients aren’t taking their medication
as prescribed at the intervention stage.
Thanks to the new medicine service, by the
follow up stage 2-3 weeks later, this number
reduces to nearly 1 in 10.
We want to be able to support as many patients
like Rob as we can, as they start their own
journey with a new medicine.
That’s why we need your help.
Every patient we identify and sign up for
NMS, is a step towards ensuring our patients
are receiving the best healthcare possible.
We do it because we care.
And It all starts by asking one simple question.